<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Breife description or character of the religion and manners of the phanatiques in generall. Scil. [brace] Anabaptists, Independents, Brovvnists, Enthusiasts, Levellers, Quakers, Seekers, Fift-Monarchy-Men, &amp; Dippers. Shewing and refuting theur absurdities by due application, reflecting much also on Sir Iohn Præcisian and other novelists. Non seria semper.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77424</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4573</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1765_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209656</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868521</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868521</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170349</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77424)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170349)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 220:E1765[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Breife description or character of the religion and manners of the phanatiques in generall. Scil. [brace] Anabaptists, Independents, Brovvnists, Enthusiasts, Levellers, Quakers, Seekers, Fift-Monarchy-Men, &amp; Dippers. Shewing and refuting theur absurdities by due application, reflecting much also on Sir Iohn Præcisian and other novelists. Non seria semper.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed, and are to be sold by most stationers;,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept: Sept. 10".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anabaptists --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Brownists --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Levellers --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170349:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BREIFE DESCRIPTION OR CHARACTER Of the Religion and Manners of the PHANATIQUES In Generall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Scil.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>ANABAPTISTS,</item>
               <item>INDEPENDENTS,</item>
               <item>BROVVNISTS,</item>
               <item>ENTHUSIASTS,</item>
               <item>LEVELLERS,</item>
               <item>QUAKERS,</item>
               <item>SEEKERS,</item>
               <item>FIFT-MONARCHY-MEN, &amp;</item>
               <item>DIPPERS.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Shewing and Refuting their Abſurdities by due Application, Reflecting much alſo on Sir <hi>Iohn Praeciſian</hi> and other Noveliſts.</p>
            <q>—Non Seria Semper—</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed, and are to be ſold by moſt Stationers; 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:170349:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170349:2"/>
            <head>The Deſcription of the PHANATIQUES In Generall.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <p>PHanatiques in generall are fancifull men whoſe tongues are tipped with Sanctity, and the name of the <hi>Spirit</hi> is <hi>this,</hi> that they know not indeed what ſpirit they are of as to profeſſion. They are a people much given to dreames and to take fancies for revelations and eary pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumtions for ſerious examination of truth.</p>
               <p>Their Religion conſiſts much in externe modes and faſhions, in adhering to ſome party or <hi>Faction,</hi> in <hi>popular</hi> and ſpecious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuations and pretenſions, in admiration of ſome mens perſons, gifts, piety, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed <hi>Zeale,</hi> in <hi>prevalencies</hi> of power, in Worldly ſucceſſes, in verball aſſurances, in looſe <hi>confidencies</hi> of being elected and predeſtinated to happineſſe, of being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Saints, Prohets,</hi> preachers in a new ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170349:3"/>way, in great <hi>Zealotries</hi> for ſome new forme or way of conſtituting diſcipline, in boldneſs to affirme or deny or doe any thing, preſuming themſelves able to doe whatſoever they <hi>fancy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Owne nothing for religion in any man or any Church which appeares not juſt after that colour, figure and <hi>notion</hi> which they are taken withal. Many have little in them, they can fancy or call Religion, but onely a fierceneſſe for that ſide which they take, a <hi>conſoriouſneſſe</hi> to all they count not theirs, brand all they like not with the marke of Antichriſt; ſome of them make every thing a ſin and errour, to which they are not inclined; Others count nothing a ſin to which they have an impulſe and are free to, as they call it. Some dote much on <hi>ſelect</hi> and <hi>covenanting</hi> congregations; others are onely for private <hi>illuminations,</hi> ſolitary ſeekings, raptures, prophetick <hi>accompliſhments,</hi> &amp;c. blown up with their own breath and other mens ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſes, ſet off all that is done in their way with <hi>Epithets</hi> of rare, holy, <hi>Spiritual,</hi> divine
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170349:3"/>ſaint-like &amp;c. they have ſuch ſelf conceits of their extraordinary gifts and abilityes that they call their preſumtions <hi>inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> their <hi>darkneſſe</hi> light, their deſſolute licentiouſneſſe, Chriſtian <hi>liberty,</hi> their fierceneſſe <hi>Zeals,</hi> ſelfe confidence a <hi>divine cal,</hi> novelties <hi>rarities,</hi> their opinions per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, diſtractions, raptures, their rave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, reaſons, their dreames oracles; ſuch ſpecious and gilded idoles <hi>Teraphims</hi> of their owne imagination their fancy forg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the ſhallow plaſnes and fowl pud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles of their owne invention, where their confuſed thoughts are oftentimes ſooner out of their mouthes than in their minds.</p>
               <p>They are meer ſlovens in their <hi>devotions,</hi> have no decent peculiar places ſet a part for holy uſes, would have no heads bare in the Church but what in reverence to their <hi>Enthuſiaſtick Spirit,</hi> imitate the unman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly <hi>Hugonots</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and preach with their hats on, are content to have their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion hatched under the wings and ſeath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of any uncleane birds, magnify what is moſt diſhoneſt and uncomely in their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170349:4"/>fooliſh <hi>ringleaders</hi> even their ignorance ſet off meerly with impudence. Wiſe men find much of theſe mens religion de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with minicall <hi>affectations</hi> of words, with ſtudied tones, antick geſtures, apiſh tricks and <hi>grimaſſes</hi> ſcurrulous expreſions, much in them is ſulſome brutiſh tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuary confuſedneſſe in their duties, all their <hi>Zeale</hi> tending meerly to profaneſs, ſupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, fordidneſſe and ſlovenlyneſſe.</p>
               <p>Nothing pleaſeth their clogged ſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acks that is old, though never ſo true no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing comes amiſſe if it be dreſſed up with novelty, they think even religion it ſelfe is never well unleſſe it be ſet forth in ſome new mode and faſhion, or unwounted ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, ſilly deluſions and babilike no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velties delighting more in things gay and new, then good and old; fanſiing all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, which is but changed though much to the worſe, even old <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> ſet on the new block of faction inplumed with the feathers of popular and paſſionate fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, ſeek to divide and deſtroy all ancient formes of Churches that they may new
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170349:4"/>modell them to their popular way of calling, to advance ſuch opinions and practiſes as no holy men of old ever knew, acted or owned for Religious, as if no duties, ceremonies or Sacraments were heretofore holy, primitively or univerſally own'd, before theſe new coyners had ſet up their mints to print their Idol of new dreſſed <hi>Spirituality</hi> and ſanctity, would ſeem wiſer, more perfect in their words and fancies, than either pious antiquity, tradition or ſcripture; as if the private fancies, ſolitary dreames and ſingle ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations of filly men and women were now more holy than Oracles.</p>
               <p>Believe no Church or religion is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently reformed till they are moſt dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrically contrary to every uſe and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the <hi>Roman,</hi> abhorring many things as Popiſh Superſtitions, Antichriſt becauſe uſed by <hi>Papiſts,</hi> affecting <hi>ſingularities</hi> and chooſing rather to fall by ſtanding alone in Separation of opinion and government than to ſeem to have any ſupport by the aſſoſiation with any former Aſſemblies.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170349:5"/>You may ſooner convert a Jew than make a Phanatique yeild to arguments that croſs him: their fancy is the God they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, faction is their Heaven, peace their hell, and the Papiſt, the Divill, they hate; for all that helpe them not, they hold Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh. To be plaine, ſo much bran, filth and Droſſe of pride, popularity, chiſme, malapertneſſe, and contempt of all men, differing in opinion from them, doe hith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erto generally appeare in the face, and manners of many of thoſe who more af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the name of gifted men and <hi>Prophets</hi> than ever the Phariſees did the title of <hi>Rabby.</hi> They will hardly ever make ſuch loves as will be ſit for ſhew-bred the corne being ground in ſuch a new beaten mill, proves full of grit and gravel.</p>
               <p>Theſe Hiſtrionick players, and vaporing preachers, in many places, ſeeke to fill the world with meer noiſe and clamours, crying down all ancient Religion as Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, turning all into ſpiritual and new prophetick gifts, (to which they highly pretend) like as thoſe cheats &amp; wanderers
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170349:5"/>do, who ſwear they have found out &amp; can ſell you the true <hi>Elixar,</hi> the Philoſophers Stone which will turn baſer mettalls into gold, while yet (poor men) their rags ſords and beggery ſufficiently confutes their rare skill proclaming to all, they more need others charity then they are any wayes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to releive any man neceſſities.</p>
               <p>Like the <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> they pretend to be as perfect as the Apoſtles, Like Comets Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alting themſelves in high notions above the ordinary reach of reaſon, in ſpirituall manifeſtations beyond plain and ordinary Chriſtians, that they are not eaſily calcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by common accounts. Covet to be called ſpirituall who walk after the fleſh, ſtudy to cover their follies and hipocriſies with the <hi>Shewes</hi> of the ſpirit of God, as if it were not enough to ſinne againſt its ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt rules and examples in Scripture ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved by the Church; unleſſe they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute alſo unto it their ſimplicities, fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, impudencies, filthy dreames, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagancies and confuſions, counting it no ſhame to aſcribe thoſe unreaſonable
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170349:6"/>abſurd motions to Gods moſt wiſe holy Spirit, which any man of right reaſon, common ingenuity and modeſty would be aſhamed to owne. It had it been better for ſuch not to have known the way of the Spirit in Scripture, far mor evenial to erre for want of the Spirits guidance and light, than to ſhut our eyes againſt it; and to impute it to our errors, dreames, darkneſſes and hipocriſies. Its better to have the heart wholy barren then to lay our adulterous baſtards to the Spirits charge; when indeed they are iſſued of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but pride joyned to ignorance, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geries and gliſtring novelties ſet off with inſolence, ſince neither the temper of their Spirits, nor their workes or words are like the rules, markes or fruites of the holy Spirit of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>They challinge the ſpirit of Chriſt in ſuch a plenary meaſure and power to themſelves, that they juſtifie their want of ordinary abilites and endowments by their <hi>needing none</hi> Excuſing their not ſtud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or preparing for what they utter by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170349:6"/>their being <hi>ſpecially inſpired,</hi> colouring over their well known idleneſs, illiterateneſs, ignorance and emptineſs, by the <hi>Shews</hi> of ſpecial <hi>illuminations,</hi> ſudden <hi>inſpirations</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual inablements.</hi> You muſt not ask them where are their <hi>Miracles?</hi> where their Empire over Devills, where their gift of languages? where their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies? theſe queſtions though juſt to be put where extraordinary <hi>Inſpirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> are pretended, are too hard for them, be they never ſo godly, if you put them one pin above their pitch, they either crack, or ſound like ſtrings overſtrained, harſhly, and out of tune.</p>
               <p>In their pretended Liberty and <hi>Level<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> Principles, they juſtifie the flagitiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their <hi>Villanies,</hi> as if the zeale they had for <hi>Religion</hi> provoked them to ſuch <hi>Outrages;</hi> then the moſt crying In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice muſt be thought the higheſt <hi>Iuſtice</hi> the moſt partiall <hi>Tolleration</hi> muſt be voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced for Chriſtian Liberty; the groſſeſt <hi>Anarchies</hi> good Government, and the moſt <hi>Novel</hi> and unjuſt Cauſe that ever
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170349:7"/>was, muſt needs be cryed up for the <hi>Good Old Cauſe.</hi> The better to ſet off their <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions</hi> and <hi>Practiſes,</hi> their Retreat is (as Foxes when eagerly hunted) to earth themſelves in <hi>This,</hi> the <hi>Spirit</hi> hath taught and dictated thoſe things unto them, or interpreted or revealed the Scripture to them in <hi>this manner,</hi> or impulſed and dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them upon ſuch and ſuch waies as are uncomely and unwonted. This is done with the ſame <hi>Falſity</hi> and Confidence as <hi>Mahomet</hi> perſwaded the credulous vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, that his fits of <hi>Falling-ſickneſſe,</hi> and the device of his Pigeon coming to his ear, where he had accuſtomed to feed it, were Monitions and Inſpirations he had from God by his Bleſſed Spirit.</p>
               <p>A vacuity with ſafety may be concluded in their <hi>Heads,</hi> whoſe bodies and <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> are filled with too much affectation and vain glory, who like <hi>Atomes Volatle</hi> and <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetled,</hi> juſtle &amp; whirle up &amp; down without incorporating any thing but Air. Their Holineſſe is meer titular and verball, like <hi>Montaniſts, Cathariſts,</hi> &amp; <hi>Gnoſticks</hi> of old, or
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170349:7"/>the later cruel and rude <hi>Phanatiques</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> who cryed <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy,</hi> to their parties and <hi>factions,</hi> as if there were holy ſeditions, holy ambitions, holy ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, holy cruelties, holy ignorances, holy confuſions, holy errors, holy <hi>Schiſmes,</hi> holy <hi>Hypocriſies</hi> in the hearts and ſpirits of ſpirituall men. Under theſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſes of extraordinary gifts of the Spirit, <hi>Architophel,</hi> and <hi>Iehu,</hi> and <hi>Iudas,</hi> and <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus,</hi> and the Sons of <hi>Sheva</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> and the ſelfe made Propheteſſe <hi>Ieza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> and <hi>Diotrophes,</hi> all falſe Prophets (and Miniſters of Satan) ſtudied to appear.</p>
               <p>If any praies publickly in matter, words, or method, approved by the <hi>practiſe</hi> &amp; <hi>tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi> of the Church, it is (they ſay) but a forme and ſtinting <hi>of the Spirit,</hi> if they preach with exactneſs and <hi>Preparation,</hi> it is not the Spirit but Study and Learning: If they read holy Bookes, tis but a dead Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and Lip-labour if they celebrate the Sacraments with Reverence and Decency, they quarrel at the Place, or Time, or Geſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure or company, or Ceremonies uſed of old.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170349:8"/>If they uſe the ancient Doxology giving Glory to the <hi>Trinity</hi> as the <hi>Greekes</hi> and Latine Churches ever did, their <hi>Socinian</hi> and <hi>Arrian</hi> Eares are ſo offended, as if Chriſtians ſhould ask them leave to own the Bleſſed Trinity, if any explicateth the <hi>Rudiments</hi> for Inſtruction, the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Chriſtian Religion, continuing ſummaries of things to be <hi>Believed,</hi> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed and <hi>Prayed</hi> for, as the <hi>Creed,</hi> the <hi>Ten Commandements,</hi> and <hi>Pater Noster,</hi> theſe men fancy them as the Recitation of ſome Charmes, and looke upon the Prieſt as ſome Exorciſt confined to theſe Articles of ſtinted Spells and Formes. If they name any Apoſtle, Evangeliſt or other Chriſtian of undoubted Sanctity with the Epithet of <hi>Saint,</hi> they are ſo ſcared with the Popes Canonizing Saints, that they ſtart at the very name ſo uſed, as if it were an unſanctified Title not to be applyed to the memory of the Bleſſed, but only arrogated to ſome perſons living, who ambitiouſly call themſelves and their party <hi>Saints.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:170349:8"/>
               <p>If any of theſe <hi>Glorioſoes</hi> and <hi>New-Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minates</hi> have any competent gifts of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as to ſomething of Religion; yet they have commonly ſomething monſtrous odd, extravagant, either vaine or <hi>Moroſe,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective or <hi>Superfluous,</hi> light or <hi>Tetricall,</hi> rude or proud, popular or affectated, and after all, the cry and noiſe, and glorying of theſe mens <hi>Inſpirings,</hi> at the beſt, all amounts to no more then but a little <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Knowledge,</hi> new <hi>gloſſed</hi> and painted over; whoſe Ignorance, Weakneſſe, and Confuſions, will only ſerve to betray and deſtroy Religion and State, but never to defend it, being more offenſive then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive; fitter for ſeduction then redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, to infect then cure. Their <hi>New-Nurſery</hi> of <hi>gifted</hi> Brethren and Prophets, are ſo AEſopick and deformed, rather fit to ſcare men from, then to inſtruct them in Holineſſe or Pyety, and by their meer Formalities, extemporary Pratings, and Contempt, to make wide Gaps and eaſie Inroads for Superſtition and Atheiſme.</p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Dreame of none but
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170349:9"/>lean Cattle in the <hi>Field</hi> of the Church; the leſſe wooll and fleſh they have on their backs, the more <hi>ſpiritual</hi> they muſt <hi>needs be;</hi> fed by thredbare <hi>hunger-ſtarv'd</hi> Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, neceſſitious &amp; whining peices of impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent ignorance, crowch and fawne on eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry plauſible Errour, on every powerfull Novelty, on every proud fancy and high imagination, prone to adorne by their gifts ſome odd opinion, and ſet it forth as a Divine Truth: Like <hi>Arelius</hi> a Painter in <hi>Iulius Caeſars</hi> time, who when he was to paint any Goddeſſe, corrupted his art by alwaies making them like ſome of his Miſtreſſes. They lick the Sores of any mens Conſcience, or the Pollutions of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mens hands, (as they did of <hi>Olivers</hi> and the <hi>Rumps</hi>) labour to turne all ſolidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Truth into nothing but <hi>Fantaſticall Whimſies,</hi> empty <hi>Notions,</hi> and ſublimity of <hi>Non-ſence.</hi> Their Affections like the poor womans Wort, is often hot in the point of Zeale, when it is very ſmall in point of judgement, and apt to run out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to much diſorder and conſuſion in ruſticall
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170349:9"/>impertinencies, and pittifull <hi>Rhapſodies</hi> of confuſed ſtuffe, ſpitting out their Poyſon like the <hi>Racovian</hi> Catechiſme, and ſuch like Primers of the Devill, againſt all Chriſtian Duties, extern Decency, and diſtinction of Order or Office; againſt all Holineſſe, Morality, and Modeſty in mens Lives.</p>
               <p>None of theſe Rabbies can content themſelves with Reſtraints of Humane or Divine Lawes, or Principles imbraced by their Anceſtors, they muſt ever have ſome new fangle of Opinion and Practiſe to make themſelves Remarkeable; for theſe ſo cryed up gifted men and Saints, if they ſhould uſe the learned helpes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens Labours, and adde nothing of the Rawneſs of their own Invention, or may not ſeem to ſay ſomething of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (being ſo full of the Spirit) like Bladders, would be forced to burſt for want of vent. We finding now a brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Light, a warmer Heate, a ſweeter Influence from theſe <hi>New Parelij,</hi> as Rivalls in brightneſſe to our old<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Id eſt</hi> Seeming and mock ſunnes, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing with the true ſun, as in <hi>Eng.</hi> 1640.</note> ſunne,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170349:10"/>and threatning now to ecclipſe it, and uttely expell it out of its ancient Orbe and Sphere. O how ſhould we emulate their bleſſedneſſe? How ſhould we be ready as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> to fall at their feet? To kiſſe their Footſteps, to attend their directions, imitate their Examples, par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate of tehir Raptures, to pry into the third Heaven in <hi>Apocalyptick Revelations,</hi> to all which in word and fancy they pretend; imagining perhaps (as ſome ſay Turks do) of Blind and Mad-men, that they have ſpeciall Viſions becauſe they want their Eyes, and extraordinary Revelations, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are deſtitute of common reaſon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of their Diſciples.</head>
               <p>Their <hi>Proſelytes</hi> are rather perverted then converted, made theirs by a factious adherence, by a fiduciary obedience, or <hi>fallacious pretenſions</hi> of the Spirits <hi>Special Motions;</hi> whoſe ſillineſſe makes them gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Spectators, and obſequious Admirers of any thing that is new to them or above them, eaſily admire what they hardlieſt underſtand, and who rather may be ſaid to be Spectators then Hearers of theſe mens <hi>affected</hi> geſticulations.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:170349:10"/>
               <p>Theſe Brazen Oratours venture to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain their Leaden Auditors, their Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed Proſelytes and ſilly Diſciples, (who like Callow Birds gape wide, and are greedy to ſwallow any thing which is brought to them) with ſtuffe of their own proper invention, impreparation, and diſcompoſure. Nothing is commonly more weak &amp; flaſhy (like Whites of Egs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Salt) nothing more looſe, ſpungy, and unſubſtantiall, then what ariſeth from no higher Source then their owne Braine, their ſudden and ſhallow Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies which (like Rheume eaſily ſwims out of their <hi>Mouths,</hi> Lips,) peſtilently er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous, nnd fanatically confuſed, moſt unwholeſome and unſavory Medleyes of filthy Faſhoods, deſperate Doctrines tempered as the Ratſ-bane of Old He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks (which <hi>Tertullian</hi> tells us of) was wont with ſome mixtures of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Texts, ſome light <hi>Inſperſions</hi> of truth to make them appetitious, paſſable, and toothſome, with their at firſt, may be, ſqueamiſh Diſciples, who by little and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170349:11"/>little (as Mithridates) wonting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to nibble and ſip of Poyſons, come to that confidence that they venture to quaff up any Draughts, who by theſe great Doſes of <hi>Mercury,</hi> occaſion rather <hi>Palſies</hi> then any <hi>Steadineſs</hi> in the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, by rendring it more bold then <hi>Rational.</hi> And the only <hi>Antidote</hi> theſe wretched Hearers have againſt thoſe or the like poyſons of Soules, is no other, but their Cuſtome of drinking of ſuch horrid and abominable Liquors, whoſe Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nome hath ſo ſtupified their Conſciences, that they are paſt all feeling and ſenſe, either of ſinn, ſhame, or ſorrow.</p>
               <p>The large <hi>Phylacteries</hi> of pretended preaching Gifts, of high Expreſſions of <hi>Zeale,</hi> which theſe men ſo Phariſaically ſet forth to the vulgar view, by which theſe cunning <hi>Quakers</hi> ſeek to loſe the eyes of their Spectators in clouds of <hi>Obſcurities</hi> and <hi>Uncertainties,</hi> and the Vulgar once dazeled with the gliſtering flaſhes of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Inſpirations, Enthuſiaſmes,</hi> and Seraphick Dictates; once in this maze
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170349:11"/>in the wood of theſe ſtrange <hi>Speculations,</hi> thoſe <hi>unwonted Notions,</hi> thoſe pretty <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerdemaines</hi> in Religion (which <hi>Fanatick juglers</hi> ſtudy more then ſolid-<hi>Piety</hi>) are not able to know where they are as to Religion, nor find out Truth to lead them out of that Fooles <hi>Paradiſe.</hi> Poor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple being doſed with <hi>Novelties,</hi> (as Larkes with dazeling Glaſſes) picking up <hi>Curioſities,</hi> or gazing at <hi>Sublimities,</hi> or dubious in uncertainties, or intangled with <hi>Subtilties,</hi> (as Deere in acorne time, forget their food,) grow lean and fall into diverſe Snares and <hi>Temptations,</hi> into many Luſts and <hi>Paſſions;</hi> many as leaves from Trees in Autumne, every day drop a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way and dye in their Mazes and <hi>Laby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinths</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> wearying themſelves in intricate <hi>Difficulties,</hi> as ſome vaine and Lunatick Chriſtians, who buſie them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves more how to interpret the <hi>Reveala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> then to underſtand the clear Precepts of the Goſpell, advancing no more in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion then Birds in a Cage, or blind Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in a Mill. Thus weake <hi>Proſelites</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170349:12"/>eaſily deluded and gulled, biaſſed and ſwerved with fair words, ſpecious pretences, and partiall Intereſts; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if their Novel Paedagogues have any ſhew, ſmack, or tincture of more than ordinary godlineſs. The moſt ſerious en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of theſe <hi>ſerious</hi> men being to <hi>cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivate</hi> the <hi>Ignorant beholders.</hi> So trade in nothing but Apes and Peacocks, Pageants of new opinions, like Pedlers of Religion vend their Toyes, Ribands, and Phana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique Rattles, till the Countrey gaping be a little over, and the gloſs of Novelty faded away.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of their Calling and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination.</head>
               <p>They pretend and fancy to be ſtamped with the mark of <hi>Popular Ordination,</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude themſelves in crowds, in illiterate heaps, without a Call from God or man, but rather from the Countreymans Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, or armed mans Trumpet; think it all one power enables them to make a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter or Prieſt, which makes a Mayor, Bayliff, or Conſtable. They take the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to ſeparate themſelves from the Clergie, and by a mutual Call of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170349:12"/>to jugge themſelves like Partridges into ſmall Coveys, which they call Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies or Churches, even before they have any Miniſter, whom they reſolve to have out of their own <hi>chooſing and ordaining,</hi> that they may be ſure to have him after their own <hi>humour.</hi> They may be as well their own Preachers and Baptizers one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter another, as ordain of themſelves any one to be, and exerciſe that power which they preſume to give to another; which they cannot do, if they have not the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer themſelves. What ſorry choice do you think they make? How weakly do they examine Sufficiencies? how wildly <hi>ordain him?</hi> what ſad and ſlovenly hands do they impoſe upon them? what croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked blocks do they hew to be their <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curies?</hi> what I dols do they ſet up to be their Shepherds, who can neither ſee nor hear, or rightly underſtand any Myſteries of Religion?</p>
               <p>They are a People rather taken with a familiar ruſticity in a Miniſter, than with the learned Abilities; prefer a <hi>Mechanick</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:170349:13"/>before a <hi>Divine;</hi> judge not what is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſt, but what is fitteſt to their fancies) receiving more willingly one that comes in his own name as gifted, or in their name as choſen and ordained by them, than if he come in Chriſts Name, ſent by his Vicegerents.</p>
               <p>Such tumours and inflamed ſwellings they have of their abilities and <hi>ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited ſufficiencies,</hi> that they think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at the firſt inſtant fitted for every work of the Sanctuary: their gifts, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and <hi>utterance</hi> are qualifications ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for them to challenge the right of <hi>ordination</hi> or publick Miniſtry, they need no other patent or <hi>Commiſſion.</hi> So they will be ploughing and ſowing when they are not apted to break the clods, and harrow the ſeed, and this ſelf-ſowing comes like to that which ſprings <hi>on the houſe top,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the mower ſhall <hi>never fill his hand, nor he that bindeth up the ſheaves his boſom.</hi> Like Apes in the Fable, fancy they can build as brave houſes, Cities, or Churches, as the ableſt men; but when they come to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170349:13"/>the Wood, they have not ſo much as Saws or Axes, or any tools to begin the work withall.</p>
               <p>Alaſs thoſe poore, but proudly <hi>gifted</hi> men, theſe <hi>ſerious</hi> people (as they term themſelves) who ſpread ſo large <hi>ſailes,</hi> hang out ſuch faire ſtreamers; and ſeek to make ſo good <hi>a ſhew</hi> to the vulgar ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, as if they were ſtrong built, well rigged, and richly loaden Veſſels, fit to endure thoſe rough Seas and ſtormes to which truth is frequently expoſed; are eaſily judged by all wiſe and learned Chriſtians to be but light keels and flat bottomed boats, by their floating ſo lof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, by their running ſo boldly over any ſhelves and rocks of opinion; which ſhews they have not the due <hi>Ballaſt,</hi> weighty Knowledge, and ſound Judegment, the want of which makes them ſo fool-hardy, apt to be toſſed to and fro with every winde of Doctrine,; ſo prone to grow leaky, either letting in under water ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly corrupt and brackiſh opinions, or ſhipping in above deck openly and boldly
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170349:14"/>whole Seas of any finiſter and worldly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts that are abroad the ſtormes, and waves and confuſions of civil affairs. And ſo by popular precipitances and licentious extravagancies, are the likelieſt to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw and bring all Chriſtianity, by <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick</hi> and <hi>Mahometan</hi> Methods, in Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſm, illiterature, confuſion and barbarity: for as they have the leaſt skill, ſo have they the moſt paſſion and unbridled vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and leaſt able to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Uſe and Abuſe of things. Whence I gather that ſaying of a wiſe man to be moſt true, That it is better in Churches, as well as in places of Civil Power, to prefer corrupt men, than weak and fooliſh men; the one is as a thief in a Vineyard, who will onely take ripe Grapes till he is ſatisfied; the other is as an Aſſe, eats ripe and green, crops the Vines, treads down much with his heels, and when his belly is full tumbles amongſt them.</p>
               <p>To <hi>Civil Affairs</hi> its likely their ſpirit prompts them as much to be medling:
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170349:14"/>but there they know how to keep their ſpirit in better order, being over-awed with evident danger attending tumultua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry motions. None of thoſe fiery Zealots are powerfully enough moved to uſurp any place in the Privie-Council, to arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate the Office or Authority of an Agent or Embaſſador, or ſet himſelf in the Seat of Juſtice uncommiſſioned; or to intrude into any place Military or Civil, without warrant from other than their own ſpirits: though their pride and ambition may whiſper them in the ear, they better diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch buſineſſes, do exacter Juſtice and ſpeedier, than any in Authority; yet the danger of penalty of intruſion cows their Zeal, curbs their heady ſpirits, and cuts their combs: nor are they often ſo vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant as to act by their pretended <hi>impulſes</hi> in any way but where they think there may be ſafety.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of their Learning.</head>
               <p>To ſpeak of <hi>their Learning,</hi> or rather ignorance, I am aſhamed to ſhame them ſo much, if I ſhould ſhew the world their emptineſs, <hi>ſhallowneſs,</hi> penury, <hi>nothingneſs,</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:170349:15"/>as to Reaſon, Religion, Learning, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Senſe: how groſs, confuſed, flat, inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid, affected they are in ſpeaking or wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting? how dark in Doctrine? how diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly in Diſputes? how impatient in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof? what perfect Battologiſts they are, what circles they make, and rounds they daunce in prayings and ſermonings, ſtrong onely in railing, cavilling, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniating. How do their pamphlets cheat the buyers with the <hi>decoy</hi> of ſome very <hi>ſpecious</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual Title,</hi> and amuſe the Readers with <hi>ſhews</hi> of <hi>rare notions,</hi> as all were <hi>Manna</hi> and <hi>Aarons Rod</hi> in their <hi>Ark,</hi> when there is nothing but <hi>Mice</hi> and <hi>Emrods,</hi> ſpurious, hypocritical, and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable <hi>dogmata,</hi> ſtrangely mutilating and deforming antient <hi>Theology</hi> in its <hi>Morals, Mysteries,</hi> and <hi>Speculations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not a dumb ſpirit, but a <hi>ſilly, prating, illiterate</hi> one poſſeſſes them. They would be counted <hi>Apoſtolical,</hi> yet are ſo far from the <hi>gift</hi> of <hi>tongues, miracles, knowledge,</hi> &amp;c. that they are ſcarce maſters of their own mother <hi>Tongue,</hi> neither knowing for the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170349:15"/>moſt part what they ſay, nor whereof they affirm, nor able with modeſty, charity, gravity and humility, to bridle or uſe their tongues. They cry out againſt all humane Learning and Studies, all <hi>Liberal Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences,</hi> againſt all Books but the <hi>Bible,</hi> againſt the <hi>Schools</hi> and <hi>Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities,</hi> as heatheniſh and <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> marks of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> as deformities and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinencies (where we have Scripture-light) prejudicial to that immediate Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine teaching to which they pretend, and by which they learn and teach all true Religion, which needs not any of thoſe rags and additional tatters of humane learning.</p>
               <p>Theſe witleſſe <hi>Lack-Latine</hi> Zealots, tell their Proſelytes and ſilly Auditors, that <hi>Latine</hi> and <hi>Greek</hi> are the Languages of the <hi>Beaſt,</hi> perſwade Chriſtians to burne all Books, that they better underſtand the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and the Bible too, that they may better underſtand the <hi>mind of God;</hi> which is all one as if the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ſhould have been perſwaded to have rid themſelves of
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170349:16"/>the cumber of their Swords, Spears and Shields, that ſo they better defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> did not diſdain to converſe with the Learned Doctors and <hi>Rabbies</hi> of his time, amongſt whom he was found after his parents had ſought him ſorrowing: yet our wanderers and ſeekers are loth to ſeek him, affraid to finde him, diſdain to own him among the Learned, leſt in ſo doing, they ſhould ſeem to confeſs they had loſt Chriſt and true Religion in their illiterate <hi>Conventicles</hi> and ignorant pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions.</p>
               <p>Theſe great <hi>ſticklers</hi> againſt Learning confute their own Principles, their folly falls on themſelves, for their deſpair of learning, makes them deſpiſe it in others; <hi>Lucifer</hi>-like they pretend <hi>light</hi> and intend <hi>darkneſs;</hi> cry up the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> which is eaſily done, that they may cry down <hi>learning,</hi> which is hardlier <hi>attained.</hi> But O how do they <hi>ſeriouſly triumph</hi> and rejoyce when any man that is but a ſmatterer of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and ſmells a little of the pen and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170349:16"/>inkhorn, ſeems to adhere and lean to them, and ſtickles for their party and faction, deceived with their <hi>ſhews</hi> of <hi>godlineſs</hi> and <hi>inſpirations.</hi> O how do they prick up their ears, and march then with greater courage (as the Hares did when they had got a Fox to lead them, in whom they thought was more ſtrength and cunning than their own fearfull feebleneſs could be <hi>guilty</hi> of:) even ſo theſe bunglers in reaſon, wreſters of Scripture, and huckſters of Religion, do finde fault with thoſe tools which they have no skill to uſe, and like cowards quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel with thoſe Weapons as unlawfull, which they moſt fear and leaſt reſiſt. As Apes, who knowing their own uncomely want of tailes, would be glad if they could bring it in faſhion for all Beaſts to have none, or perſwade them to cut off (as burthens and deformities) thoſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern <hi>ornaments</hi> of the body wherewith na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath furniſhed the nobler, <hi>comelier,</hi> and ſtronger creatures.</p>
               <p>What would theſe <hi>illiterate furies</hi> give to have indeed ſuch an <hi>Illumination</hi> as
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170349:17"/>might in one night make them as learned and able in all points as the <hi>Scotiſts, Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, Sorboniſts,</hi> and other learned men are, who detect theſe Mountebancks, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover theſe deceitful workers, and ſet theſe cheats in the Pillory of publick infamy, to loſe their ears, <hi>at tandem male audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt qui male dicunt &amp; agunt,</hi> paring their under nails, and muzling the bolder jawes of this <hi>ferine faction</hi> of theſe deſperate and <hi>degenerate Chriſtians,</hi> who like <hi>Balaams</hi> beaſt, or as <hi>horſe and Mule being without underſtanding,</hi> are ready to fall upon thoſe that are fit to be their Maſters and rulers both in Church and State. Who inſtead of ſound learning, have confident igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, or <hi>fraudulent</hi> and <hi>flattering</hi> errors or <hi>factious ſemblances</hi> of truth to uſher in damnable and Heterodox Doctrines, and in lieu of excellent literature, have onely the three diſtempers at height which Sir <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> (in his advancement of lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) obſerved to be in moſt men <hi>fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtickneſs, contention</hi> and <hi>curioſity,</hi> by <hi>ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, altercation,</hi> and <hi>affectation.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:170349:17"/>
               <p>Firſt, Comparing themſelves with themſelves, they fancy they grow <hi>holier,</hi> as they grow <hi>bolder</hi> in their opinions and actions: hence they are eaſily flatered into high <hi>imaginations,</hi> and cheated with ſtrong preſumptions, as if ſome common gifts of knowledge, ſome <hi>ſceptical quickneſs,</hi> ſome <hi>volubility</hi> of <hi>utterance,</hi> ſome ſcriptural ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions which they have attained be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond their former ſelves or <hi>equals,</hi> were <hi>rare, immediate,</hi> and <hi>ſpecial gifts</hi> of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. Then becauſe they ſhould ſeem no body if they carry their ſmall wares in an old pack, they invent ſome new faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Religion, or model of Church-way they fancy moſt. Then follow thoſe <hi>quick Emotions</hi> and ſtirrings upon their ſpirits (which have the <hi>quickning</hi> only of <hi>ſelf</hi> in them) theſe are preſently cried up for motions, <hi>manifeſtations, excitations,</hi> and <hi>impulſes</hi> of Gods Spirit on them. Then they are moved to extraordinary heats, and irregular vehemencies, and <hi>illegal irregularities,</hi> as <hi>counterfeit poſſeſſed</hi> are. Theſe fond conceits of their <hi>improvements</hi>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:170349:18"/>and perfections, makes them, like care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs children, forſake the lap of their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther before they can ſtand by themſelves, and think themſelves Sophies before they arrive to be Sophiſters; or fit Pilots to ſteer the Ship of the Church, when they are very mean Skippers and Skullers.</p>
               <p>The varity of their conceits, mixtures and inventions, firſt kindle with modeſt ſparks, as if they would <hi>enlighten,</hi> warm, and refine Religion; but after they have got to them vulgar fewel, they ariſe to ſuch dreadfull flames and conflagrations, as threaten to conſume all that was ever built before them. Poor men, thus once puffed up with their <hi>timpanies</hi> and <hi>ſelf-conceptions,</hi> having once over-looked their firſt errors, they never after have leiſure, patience or humility, to diſcern the groſs yet ſecret diſtempers which are in their ſpirits, the many <hi>diſtinctions, diſguiſes</hi> and windings, by which worldly paſſions and intereſts ſlily creep in, and concealedly work in their hearts, even then moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly (and ſo moſt dangerouſly) when
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170349:18"/>under this <hi>blind of Gods Spirit,</hi> when the Lord ſhall be <hi>intitled</hi> to their whole plot and project of their follies and furies.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Doct.</head>
               <p>Trace them a little farther in their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and you will finde them to tread much awry. They are a People taught to be tumultuary againſt you, and imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous upon you. Teach that evil of ſin may be done, that publick good may come thereby.</p>
               <p>They permit divorces in ſleight cauſes, affect parity and reject Tithes as ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious and <hi>judaical;</hi> they admit private men to adminiſter the Sacraments; and in ſome places commit the power of the keys to women; in preaching they will not be tied to any Text, nor in praying to any Form; in communicating they ſit at Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, or have no Table at all; and becauſe they would not ſeem too <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> in the time of <hi>adminiſtration,</hi> they are covered. They love not the old names of Churches (which they ſleightly call Steeple-hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,) of the daies of the week, of the moneths of the year, of <hi>Chriſtmas, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaelmas,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170349:19"/>Candlemas,</hi> &amp;c. in their Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacks all Saints daies muſt be obliterated, <hi>alias</hi> their pious (but mendacious Progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticator) <hi>William Lilly</hi> had not ſo long kept ſanctity with them.</p>
               <p>They are affraid to meddle with any thing that ever paſſed the Popes fingers, except onely the Lands and Revenues of the Clergie; leave nothing to maintain Religion or its Miniſtry, but the ſcraps of arbitrary and grudging Contributions: Like <hi>Don Quixots</hi> and Knights-Errant, have ſo many <hi>Romances,</hi> forms, and <hi>idaea's</hi> of Religion in their heads, which makes them admirable but not imitable; have ſuch <hi>ferocious</hi> ſpirits like pampered horſes whom no ground will hold, neighing after novelties, and give way to long-winded extemporary ſpecious nonſenſe above the common capacity. If any wiſe man comes to hear them, he ſoon finds them as dark and dusky as if they had been begotten in the eclipſe of the Sun, and born in the laſt quarter of the Moon. The heat of theſe <hi>Rotomontadoes</hi> by their over-charged and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170349:19"/>ill-diſcharged zeal, uſually breaks it ſelf in ſunder in its abettors, aſſiſtants and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctators, with ſuch inchanting Opinions that they make God the Patronizer of their Villanies, Murders, Tyrannies and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and boaſt how clearly it might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear God owned their Cauſe and diſown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Adverſaries, urging Gods per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions againſt his Precepts and Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as though Gods toleration of evil, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, ſchiſms, diſorders, &amp;c. did juſtifie them againſt his Word and Church that forbids them. Pretend the Spirit to be Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron of their moſt extravagant fancies, the deviſer of their moſt incredible opinions, and dictator of their moſt indemonſtrable <hi>dreams</hi> and <hi>new revelations.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>They like no humble, ſober, and exact ties of conſcience, and duties of true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, by which holy men in all ages have given diligence to make ſure their calling and election, to work out their ſalvation with <hi>fear and trembling,</hi> by repenting, faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, watching, prayer, by judging and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170349:20"/>condemning their ſinfull ſelf, by mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and ſelf-denial, coming to the Croſs of Chriſt, taking it up, and bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to all patient ſufferings. Theſe are harder <hi>diſciplines,</hi> rougher ſeverities, ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter Doctrines of piety, than our delicate <hi>Noveliſts,</hi> our <hi>gentle Enthuſiaſts,</hi> our tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing <hi>Libertines,</hi> our <hi>ſofter Saints,</hi> can endure, who contrary to the examples of good <hi>old Chriſtians</hi> and <hi>Martyrs,</hi> glory not in <hi>croſſes</hi> but in Crowns, not in buffets but in raptures, not in being counted ſinners, but Saints, not in ſelf-denyings, but in ſelf-intereſſes, not crucified to the world, but crucifiers of the world, not ſuffering from the world, but triumphing in the world.</p>
               <p>They are in fancy as the <hi>Argonautae</hi> brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of the golden Fleece, the Riches of Righteouſneſs of Chriſt, the Treaſures of Heaven, the true Gold of <hi>Ophir,</hi> pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that God is their Father, that they are <hi>Saints</hi> and ſpiritual inſpired Prophets, ſent of God to call the world to repentance, to reign with Chriſt, &amp;c. in ſuch conceited confidencies, proud hypocriſies, ſoft fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacies,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170349:20"/>rotten ſenſualities, libidinous ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creſcencies, like <hi>Eſtrike</hi> birds, ſet forth their ſoft and gay feathers (having but little bodies but leſs brains) by wandring from their neſts, their Shops and Looms, Thimbles and Bodkins (the ſtations wherein moſt of them have been bred up) and from which they have no ſufficient rule from God or man to move them, having at the beſt but very moderate gifts, not tried or approved by any wiſe men, but onely blown up by the pittifull applauſes of ſome ſilly men and women, with levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, gapings, ſwellings, <hi>hollowneſs, crooked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and <hi>weakneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe curious <hi>Speculatiſts</hi> recite may be by rote ſome raw and <hi>fejume Notions</hi> and diſorderly <hi>Meditations</hi> (which weak men call prophecying) with much error, froth, and vanity, incident to theſe ſelf-oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Gifts, which have more of the tongue than heart or head, and oft times reſemble more the <hi>Player</hi> than the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher. <hi>Narciſſus</hi>-like, they are ſo deluded with the flattering echo's of their ſilly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirers,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170349:21"/>and ſo taken with their own fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion in ſuch falſe glaſſes, that they are like to doat till they die, and ſtarve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as to all <hi>real ſufficiencies,</hi> by the fond <hi>imaginations</hi> of how great they have, and their ignorance of how much indeed they want.</p>
               <p>Much of theſe mens temper and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and after the ſame riotous faſhion, was that ignorant and abominable rabble of the <hi>Circumcelliones</hi> (a ſubſection of the <hi>Donatiſts</hi>) who were wont to ramble idly up and down like ſquibs with fire and force, till after great <hi>oſtentations</hi> of piety and devotion, and zeal for martyrdome, calling themſelves <hi>duces Sanctorum,</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains of the Saints, and Contenders for the Faith: they fell at length to pilfering, then to plundering and waſting whole Countreys, oppoſing in an hoſtile manner the Vicegerents of the Emperour <hi>Honori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us;</hi> at length were by him deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Religion, Perjury,</hi> innocent bloodſhed and Sacriledge, are drawn on by them like ſtreight and pinching ſhooes at firſt,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170349:21"/>with the ſhooing-horn of Religion and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,</hi> with <hi>antipathies</hi> againſt <hi>Idolatry</hi> and abhorrencies of <hi>Superſtition:</hi> and the better to ſet off their skill, they make, as <hi>Herod,</hi> moſt <hi>artificial</hi> Speeches, mixed with preaching and praying; and ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of Scripture, and <hi>Gods Cauſe;</hi> or as Mountebanks, make large haranges, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and popular Orations, as <hi>gilded bitter</hi> pills to give the better <hi>Guſto.</hi> In this wiſe theſe Huckſters and Cheats of Religion (as the <hi>Magicians</hi> of <hi>Egypt</hi>) ſometimes ſo enchant and delude poor credulous ſouls, that they believe all that comes from them to be <hi>miraculous;</hi> abuſing or changing glow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worms for Stars, counterfeit with <hi>cropt opinions,</hi> and round-headed Tenents with full weight of Chriſtian <hi>Doctrine,</hi> ſtill cogging with religious dice, and cheating with plauſible Fallacies (ſeemingly brought out of Scripture) until poor Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, like the bewitched <hi>Galatians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 3.</note> have loſt all or moſt of their true faith and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief. Yea ſome of theſe Impoſtors do not leave poor Chriſtians whom they have
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170349:22"/>cozened with fair <hi>ſhews</hi> of the Spirits <hi>reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations</hi> and <hi>new Goſpels,</hi> ſo much true faith as to believe the Articles of <hi>Chriſtian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</hi> And for the better colour, ſome of them pretend to ſet up (as <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> did) the Kingdom of <hi>righteouſneſs,</hi> the Throne and Scepter of <hi>King Ieſus:</hi> Yet this is but a decoy to <hi>intrap</hi> the vulgar; for who will not ſeem willing to ſubmit to Chriſts Kingdom? But we are better taught than to expect his Kingdom to be of this world.<note place="margin">Joh. 18.16.</note> — But afterwards when their phanatick power comes to be <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount,</hi> you will finde no ſuch lenities and gentle ſalves, then in popular Propoſals and <hi>levelling Principles</hi> with <hi>Goliabs</hi> of <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed</hi> enormities, they are much for a new <hi>Paracelſian practice,</hi> unexperienced Applications, and Chymical Extractions; then with the Sword of blood they can be merry in peoples miſeries, with, <hi>Populus vult decipi decipiatur,</hi> like <hi>Muncer</hi> and <hi>Knipperdoling, Hacket</hi> and <hi>Arthington.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe preſumptious <hi>Phaetons</hi> never think they enlighten the Church enough, unleſs they
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170349:22"/>ſet Kingdoms and States on fire. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the method of thoſe rare cures they ſometimes wrought in <hi>Germany</hi> about the year 1530. by the ſlaughter of an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred thouſand people, in the Anabaptiſt and phanatique ways of mutiny and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. To be ſhort, in the firſt broach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and after drawings forth of their new Doctrine, projects and inventions, the Authors of them more look upon men than <hi>God,</hi> how it may ſuit with ſecular <hi>aimes</hi> and intereſts, than the practice of <hi>Antiquity.</hi> Like the <hi>Hantons</hi> of the <hi>Swiſſe</hi> become willing upon the leaſt apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of advantage to plant the ſame <hi>Engines</hi> and weapons againſt the <hi>wrong</hi> ſide as the <hi>right.</hi> And their late minted <hi>Doctrinals</hi> verminly bred out of the putrefactions of mens brains, and the corruptions of the times, ſerve in ſome ſort to ſcratch itch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ears to ſome tune of <hi>liberty,</hi> pleaſures, profit or <hi>preferment;</hi> while they clamour like <hi>Demetrius</hi> and his <hi>Complices,</hi> in his pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick fears for his ſilver and <hi>Diana,</hi> where he conſidered more his gain than his God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſs.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:170349:23"/>
               <p>Some, though fiery, yet are orderly and patient in Government; though they excell in gifts, yet are not ſwelled with tumours; but theſe are as unſavoury ſalt, that is good for nothing, unleſs it be new boiled in an <hi>Independent</hi> or <hi>levelling</hi> Caul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dron, over a <hi>Socinian</hi> furnace with <hi>a popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar fire:</hi> they are proud, forward and preſumptuous, like the Giant who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed of his vaſt limbs and extraordinary number of his fingers and toes, <hi>ſc.</hi> 24. have ſuch extraordinary excreſcencies, which exceed mens noſes, or blind their eyes; ſometimes ſwelling bigger than their heads. Being drunk with their own fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, ſometimes reel and ſtumble upon <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions metaphyſical,</hi> which vainly puffe them up, while they are ſtill Wells without Water, deep, but dark and dry in their profound follies and profane nicities. Or clouds without moiſt exhalations, carried with the tempeſts of paſſion and high pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions, above the plain and practical way of true Chriſtians, and indeed above the proportion and ſphere of their Gifts and Parts.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:170349:23"/>
               <p>A little goes a great way with theſe <hi>il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>literates</hi> in their ſuppoſed <hi>inſpirations,</hi> and where they cannot go far on, they go round in circling <hi>tautologies,</hi> ſnarled repe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions, intricate confuſions, which are ſtill the ſame skains of thread which other men have handſomely ſpun and wound up in better method and order, which theſe men have neither skill nor patience to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, but pull out here a thread and there an end, which they break off abrubtly, to the confounding of all method, order, and proportion, Divine or Moral.</p>
               <p>In their new Models of <hi>Independent, le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling, quaking,</hi> and <hi>anabaptiſtick ſcabious</hi> Congregations, they fold up the curtains of the true Church ſo ſhort and narrow, to ſuch ſmall figures, and obſure <hi>Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles</hi> and <hi>Paucities,</hi> that they will ſcarce allow the whole company of true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in the world to be ſo great as would fill one <hi>Iewiſh Synagogue;</hi> being (as <hi>Pygmali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> with his Image) enamoured with their corpuſculoes, the little Flock and new Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of their Churches, or rather meeting-places,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170349:24"/>ſhutting themſelves up into ſome blind corners, and confining Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to obſcure Cells and ſilly Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies where in ſtead of the Suns faire light of true Reaſon, good Learning, and ſound Religion, men ſhould like Owls and Bats, and Moles, onely howl, chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and foratch one another in the dark. They are the kind of <hi>Animals</hi> which curſe the day, cannot abide the light, becauſe their eyes are weak, their works are dark, and both minds and manners are depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               <p>Having preſented them to you in <hi>groſs,</hi> I will now give you them in their <hi>Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</hi> They are a fond and fraudulent, pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſillanimous and frothy Generation of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perers; <hi>Plagiaries</hi> who infect the common air of Chriſtian Charity, Order and Peace; bring forth out of the rude mould of their own invention, nothing but diſorder: they are the left Band of <hi>Babels</hi> Builders, fit Inſtruments to divide, confound, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, but never to plant and cultivate; whoſe lips never yet dropped like <hi>Hermon</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170349:24"/>ſo much as a dew of ſweet and wholſome knowledge on any place. They are a riot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, promiſcuous and incompoſed rabble, a <hi>ſwarm</hi> of ignorant <hi>Quacks,</hi> preaching <hi>Mountebanks</hi> of the rude and vulgar, of no value, <hi>Mahometan</hi> Juglers, religious Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopolizers, pious Impoſtors, devout De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, angelized <hi>Satans, ſanctified Demons, Bells</hi> and <hi>Dragons</hi> of phanatique Divinity, as the cheating <hi>Pontifs</hi> of the heathen gods and Oracles, ſit ſtill in their lazie and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned ignorance, expecting miraculous illuminations and aſſiſtancies, like ſeiled Pigeons, the leſs they ſee, the higher they ſoar in airy, light, and high-flying <hi>fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> as moon-ey'd horſes, whoſe light follows the flux of reflux of the <hi>mad Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net, blaunch</hi> and <hi>ſtart</hi> more by <hi>day</hi> than <hi>night.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There are (ſaith <hi>Plato in Timaeo</hi>) two diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes of the ſoul, Madneſs and Ignorance: madneſs is from the abounding with pride and paſſion; ignorance, from the want of knowledge and inſtruction; thoſe men are infected with both diſtempers. For
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170349:25"/>they are a People given over to <hi>dementation</hi> and aſtoniſhment, <hi>blindneſs</hi> and <hi>madneſs,</hi> to ſeek after and truſt in lying <hi>vanities</hi> and deſperate hypocriſies, to reſt in the flattery of vulgar ſucceſſes; who think every one that proſpers a Saint or good Angel, and every one that is unfortunate a Devil or great Offender, as the <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians did S. Paul</hi> when the Viper <hi>ſeized</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his hand and he ſhook it off unhurt. They judge of Spiritual Gifts by bare and barren forms, by <hi>ſoft inſinuations</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions, by melancholy <hi>ſowreneſs, pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſaical</hi> frowns, bold aſſertions, <hi>audacious</hi> adventures, and <hi>ſucceſſefull inſolencies.</hi> Fly to their enchantments, by uſing much Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture <hi>expreſſion,</hi> by following popular ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monings, haſty aſſurances, uncharitable deſpiſings, by affecting an odde kinde of canting way of writing and ſpeaking: Pretending to Sanctity, thorow Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and advancing the Kingdom of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; to Raptures, Enthuſiaſmes, holy Convulſions, and Revelations, and ſuch like <hi>quaking and quacking</hi> tricks: con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juring
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170349:25"/>up ſtrange hopes, fears and <hi>jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies,</hi> like ſo many <hi>Ghoſts</hi> and <hi>Goblins</hi> to ſcare and amaze the common people.</p>
               <p>Like <hi>Ambulatory Arabs</hi> and wandring <hi>Scythians,</hi> they muſt every week or month change their quarters, to vend their tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent and damnable Doctrines, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring diſeaſes like the running gout from one part to another, more dangerous than the plague or <hi>epidemical malady,</hi> breathing out nothing but aſhes and cinders, like <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuvius</hi> and <hi>Aetna,</hi> whoſe eruptions are va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtutions to all near them. They are fit to be followers of <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals,</hi> or liſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>Iack Cade</hi> or <hi>Watt Tyler,</hi> or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to <hi>Iohn Bowld</hi> a Tayler of <hi>Leyden,</hi> who aſſumed the Title of <hi>Rex juſtitiae hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus mundi,</hi> King of Juſtice of this world. Or to <hi>Iohn Williams</hi> the laſt King of <hi>Sion</hi> and of this <hi>mad tribe,</hi> who had at once twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty wives; and wore by his ſide the great <hi>Gideons</hi> Sword ſent him from Heaven, as he gave out: who exhorted his Subjects and Brethren the Phanatique Anabaptiſts to look upon all other Nations and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170349:26"/>as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did upon the <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neans</hi> and others of the Land of Promiſe: but at length he was burnt at <hi>Clave, Anno</hi> 1580.</p>
               <p>You may finde theſe modern <hi>Knipper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolings</hi> amongſt the Hierarchy of handy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craftſmen, in the Kingdome of the fifth <hi>Monarchy</hi> men, at the meeting-places of <hi>Iames Naylor</hi> the late Separatiſt, amongſt the <hi>Rumps</hi> mourners, or the ſcattered ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate bodies of the late <hi>decimo ſexto</hi> edition, or in the Court of Juſtice they lately ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in <hi>Ireland,</hi> from whence they have driven the Gentry and Nobility, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpated the Natives. They were a Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natique livery compoſed of <hi>ſelf-confidence, intolerable boaſtings,</hi> of ſequaciouſneſs, of feminine <hi>ſoftneſse,</hi> of lying Prophecies, of <hi>violent Zealotries,</hi> of ſwelling <hi>excreſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> and loud clamours and empty noiſes of <hi>reformation.</hi> They have a head compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the threads of Faction, and wear a long ſword of <hi>deſtruction;</hi> you may eaſily know them by the <hi>gogle</hi> of their eye, by their <hi>pale and wan</hi> looks, by the <hi>queint</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170349:26"/>of their <hi>groaning devotion,</hi> by the <hi>counterfeit</hi> current of their <hi>ſanctified</hi> tears, by their godly way and <hi>zeal,</hi> which late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made them aſpire to the Pulpit, and renounce the awle and the anvill, and ſet up a new Exchange for Religion at the charges of the honeſt party. To conclude my Anatomy, I will epitomiſe them in a line or two more.</p>
               <p>They are mothy and moungril <hi>Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants, Centaures</hi> in the Church, half Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icks and half Laicks, the by-blows of the Clergie, gifted <hi>hypocrites,</hi> ſevere <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſſes,</hi> a whineing people, tribolary Chriſtians, new dwindling Divines, the <hi>prophetical Pigmies</hi> of this age; unordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, unbleſt, untried, unclean ſpirits, whoſe calling, commiſſion, and tenure depends on <hi>popularity,</hi> flattery and beggery; their excellency conſiſts in <hi>tautologiſing,</hi> in praying <hi>ex tempore,</hi> that is, out of all time, without order or method; being eminent in nothing above the <hi>Plebeian</hi> pitch and vulgar proportion. They ſpin out their Sermons at their wheels, or weave them
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170349:27"/>up at their looms, or dig them out with their ſpades, weigh or meaſure them in their ſhops, or ſtitch and cobble them with their Thimble and Laſts; or thraſh them out with their Flayles, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward preach them in ſome Barn to their duſty <hi>diſciples;</hi> who the better to ſet off the oddneſs of their ſilly Teachers, fancy themſelves into ſome imaginary perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as if they were thus driven into dens and caves, and woods. Their holy and learned Academies, where they firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this chymical new Divinity, and are ſince come to ſo great proficiency, were <hi>Munſters Revelations, Geneva</hi>'s <hi>Calviniſm, Amsterdams Toleration,</hi> and <hi>New-Englands Preciſeneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their Plantation ſprung firſt from the putrified part of <hi>Iohn Calvin,</hi> who being branded with <hi>Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Sodomy</hi> in his own Countrey of <hi>Picardy,</hi> retired to <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goleſme,</hi> where he went by the name of <hi>Deparcan;</hi> there he copied his <hi>Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> ſtealing the greateſt part out of the Works of <hi>Melancton</hi> and <hi>Hiperius Sarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius;</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:170349:27"/>or as <hi>Weſtphally</hi> the <hi>Lutheran</hi> ſaith, he ſtole all from <hi>Oeclampadius.</hi> Thence he went to <hi>Germany,</hi> and came at length as in regreſſion to <hi>Geneva.</hi> Where this our headleſs (yet fancifull) <hi>Monſter</hi> by Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> was begotten on an <hi>Elders</hi> Maid, and afterwards impt upon the ſtocken of Schiſme by <hi>Knox</hi> and <hi>Buchanan,</hi> and brought up after the reformed faſhion of the Scotch Kirk, for propagation of the Goſpel and better reformation, creeping into this Nation, and thus multiplied and increaſed by the phanatique lechery of the <hi>laſcivious</hi> Rump-Parliament and <hi>Olivers</hi> Redcoats.</p>
               <p>They are crafty enough to do evil, but to do good they have no knowledge or honeſty; they have hands active enough, but corrupt and baſe ends; ſecular inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts wrapped up under ſpecious pretenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of piety. Like Water-men, while they look one way they row another. They abuſe Learning to abett Errors; and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, to colour <hi>hypocriſie;</hi> and the name of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> to indulge the fleſh; and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170349:28"/>Heaven, to carry on <hi>earthly deſigns.</hi> They miſtake anger for <hi>zeal,</hi> dreams for <hi>reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,</hi> memory for <hi>conſcience,</hi> Enthuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſms for Propheſies; to wave flattery they fall into <hi>incivility;</hi> and to avoid <hi>pride,</hi> into <hi>baſeneſs.</hi> They are <hi>worthy</hi> of <hi>themſelves,</hi> and wiſer mens <hi>pity.</hi> If they have truth enough to ſave any man, they have uncharitableneſs enough to damne any Angels.</p>
               <p>Theſe Lines perfectly deſcribing all or moſt of our Fantaſticks in general, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit their particular opinions to more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Remonſtrances, this very Relation being a ſufficient Confutation.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
